const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Which of the following theories was NOT proposed by Sigmund Freud?","options":{"A":"The topographical model of mind","B":"Affect trauma theory","C":"Individual psychology theory","D":"The structural model of the mind","E":"Psychosexual stages of development"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"All of the theories listed in the question except Individual Psychology Theory were proposed by Sigmund Freud. Individual psychology theory was put forward by Alfred Adler. According to Freud’s Affect Trauma Theory, feelings that are connected to unacceptable memories are strangulated by mental mechanisms leading to neurosis. Freud divided neurosis into ‘actual’ and ‘psychoneurosis’. Actual neurosis manifested itself in anxiety neurosis or hypochondriasis. Psychoneurosis comprised of hysteria, obsessional neurosis, and phobias. Freud thought that psychoneurosis was amenable to psychoanalysis. In the Topographical Model, the mind is divided into the unconscious, preconscious, and conscious. The Structural Model of the Mind consists of the id, ego, and superego (a useful mnemonic is that S of structural model is shared with superego). Freud also came up with the stages of psychosexual development. In this, each stage of development is thought to build on and to subsume the accomplishments of the preceding stage: the oral stage (12 to 18 months of life), anal stage (18 to 36 months), phallic stage (3 to 5 years), latency stage (5 to 11 years), and genital stage (11 years to adulthood). Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 195–200."},{"question":"Which of the following is true about primary process thinking?","options":{"A":"It fulfi ls the reality principle","B":"It fulfi ls the pleasure principle","C":"It is associated with delay in gratifi cation","D":"It is ruled by rational thinking","E":"It is ruled by the concept of time"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Primary process thinking fulfi ls the pleasure principle. According to Freud, in the Topographical Model of the mind, the unconscious system is characterized by primary process thinking. Primary process thinking refers to a mode of thinking whose main aim is to facilitate wish fulfi lment. It is governed by the pleasure principle and does not follow a logical course. The concept of time is not used to streamline primary process thinking. In addition, primary process thinking allows contradictions to exist simultaneously. The conscious system receives sense impressions from the outside world and follows secondary process thinking. This is ruled by time, rational–logical thinking, and the reality principle. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 195."},{"question":"All of the following are functions of ego EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Accommodating the ego ideal","B":"Control and regulation of instinctual drives","C":"Rational judgement","D":"Mediation between the internal world and external reality","E":"Capacity to form mutually satisfying relationships"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The important functions of ego include the capacity to control the discharge of instinctual drives, the capacity to test reality, mediating between the id and the realities of the outside world (reality principle as against pleasure principle), and thus facilitating the formation of relationships. Judgement, which involves the ability to anticipate the consequences of actions, is also a function of the ego. In Freud’s psychoanalytic theory of personality, the ego ideal is the part of the superego that includes the rules and standards for good behaviours (e.g. parental discipline). Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 200.128 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Carol is undergoing psychotherapy. During her therapy sessions, she begins to argue with her therapist as she had argued with her deceased father. Which of the following phenomenon is she demonstrating?","options":{"A":"Transference","B":"Resistance","C":"Free association","D":"Catharsis","E":"Repression114 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"This is an example of transference during psychotherapy. Transference is the process by which the patient displaces wishes and feelings toward persons from the past onto the analyst. Sometimes this leads to the emergence of resistance as patients experience the psychiatrist as a parental fi gure from the past (in this case the patient’s dead father), and they seek to rebel against the perceived parental control. Resistance refers to an unconscious behaviour intended to frustrate the progress of therapy. Free association is the process where the client spontaneously expresses their thoughts and feelings as they occur. Repression is a defence mechanism. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 337."},{"question":"Which of the following refers to the mechanism by which several unconscious wishes can be combined into a single image in the manifest dream content?","options":{"A":"Displacement","B":"Symbolic representation","C":"Secondary revision","D":"Condensation","E":"Dream work"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The phenomenon described is called condensation. According to Freud, a dream is the disguised fulfi lment of an unconscious wish. Freud described two layers of dream content – the manifest and the latent. The manifest content is what the dreamer recalls; the latent content involves the unconscious thoughts and wishes that threaten to awaken the dreamer. The unconscious process by which latent dream content is changed into manifest dream is called the dream work. This dream work involves primary process revision (different from primary process thinking) and secondary revision/ elaboration. Primary process includes the mechanisms of condensation, displacement, and symbolic representation. Condensation, as described in this question, is the mechanism by which several unconscious wishes can be combined into a single image in the manifest dream content. Displacement refers to the transfer of energy from an original object to a different one. In symbolic representation of a wish or object, the original but highly unacceptable theme changes in physical qualities to a more acceptable object. This may be characterized by seemingly unrelated and absurd images. Secondary revision is the process by which dreams are made relevant and more rational when narrated to a third person. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/ Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 193"},{"question":"According to Adler, a sense of inadequacy and weakness that is universal and inborn is called","options":{"A":"Inferiority complex","B":"Organ inferiority","C":"Birth order theory","D":"Masculine protest","E":"Individual psychology"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Adler coined the term inferiority complex which is a sense of inadequacy and weakness that is universal and inborn. Masculine protest is the tendency to move from a passive, feminine role to a masculine, active role. A child’s self esteem may be compromised by a physical defect; this phenomenon is called organ inferiority. According to Adler’s birth order theory the fi rstborn child reacts with anger to the birth of siblings and struggles against giving up the powerful position of being the only child. The second-born child must always compete with the fi rstborn. This apparently results in lifelong infl uences on character and lifestyle. All the above terms, including individual psychology, were proposed by Alfred Adler. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 214.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 129"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a concept proposed by Melanie Klein?","options":{"A":"Paranoid schizoid position","B":"Reaction formation","C":"Splitting","D":"Depressive position","E":"Projective identifi cation"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Reaction formation is one of many Freudian defences. Kleinian defences can be remembered using the mnemonic (SIPDOG – splitting, introjection, projective identifi cation, denial, omnipotence, and grandiosity). According to Klein, projection and introjection are the primary defence operations in the fi rst few months of life. Soon after birth and thereafter, the infant experiences a fear that he is falling apart. This fear of fragmenting or disintegration is central to further Kleinian processes. To deal with this fear, the infant resorts to splitting, introjection, and projection. All events and perceptions are schemed into good and bad elements (splitting); the good part gets introjected, while bad part is projected onto the mother leading to persecutory anxiety. At this stage, the infant is in a paranoid–schizoid position, where the capacity to integrate varied experiences into unifi ed concept is lacking. Soon the baby comes to know that the mother he loved (when feeding) and the mother he hated (when hurt) are one and the same. Now the infant becomes concerned that he might destroy the mother due to his aggressive impulses, and the infant is said to be in a grief-like depressive position. Projective identifi cation is a Kleinian defence mechanism where unwanted feelings are projected to the other person, and he/she is made to feel and act accordingly. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 340."},{"question":"With which of the following developmental phases is Margaret Mahler associated?","options":{"A":"Anal phase","B":"Autistic phase","C":"Conventional morality phase","D":"Individuality vs inferiority phase","E":"Operational stage"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Margaret Mahler described the process by which children develop a separate identity from their mothers. She called this the theory of separation individuation (SI). Stages of separation individuation are: normal autism (birth to 2 months) where the infant sleeps most of the time, this phase is reminiscent of intrauterine life; Stage of symbiosis (2 to 5 months) where the mother and her child exist more or less as a single entity; differentiation (5 to 10 months), wherein physical and psychological distinctness from mother is gradually appreciated; practicing (10 to 18 months), where the child shows an increase in exploration of the outside world; rapprochement (18 to 24 months) where the child explores further away from the mother but on realizing the separation, comes back clinging; and object constancy (2 to 5 years) where the child realizes the permanence of the mother even when the mother is not from the vicinity (this is different from object permanence). Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 29."},{"question":"Avoiding the awareness of some painful aspect of reality by negating sensory data is called","options":{"A":"Reaction formation","B":"Projection","C":"Denial","D":"Suppression","E":"Repression"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"This is denial. The defence of denial is usually an unconscious process (I love that man becomes I do not love that man). Projection is where specifi c wishes, impulses, and aspects of self are imagined to be located in some other object external to oneself (e.g. a miser calling others ‘misers’). Projection is thought to be involved in the formation of persecutory delusions. Repression is expelling or withholding an idea or feeling from consciousness. Primary repression is when the idea has never reached consciousness at all. Secondary repression is when it has reached the conscious level at some time in the past, but is now not available for conscious processing. Suppression is consciously or semiconsciously postponing attention and response to an impulse or confl ict. This is a mature defence mechanism. Reaction formation is the transformation of an unacceptable impulse to the very opposite (I love that man becomes I hate that man). Rycroft C. A Critical Dictionary of Psychoanalysis, 2nd edn. Penguin Reference, 2005, p. 125. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/ Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 207.130 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a mature defence mechanism?","options":{"A":"Isolation","B":"Altruism","C":"Humour","D":"Anticipation","E":"SublimationPSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 115"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Isolation is a neurotic defence. It is separating an idea from the emotion that accompanies it. Defence mechanisms can be psychologically healthy or maladaptive, though their primary aim is to reduce a psychological confl ict. Psychologically healthy mechanisms can be grouped as mature defences. Various mature defence mechanisms include sublimation, altruism, humour, suppression, and anticipation. Altruism is using constructive service to provide for others without any conscious direct or indirect benefi ts. Humour is the process of using comedy to express feelings and thoughts without personal discomfort. Anticipation is realistically planning for a predicted inner discomfort. For example, a man with a terminal illness prepares his advance directives. Sublimation is achieving gratifi cation by altering a socially objectionable aim or objective to a socially acceptable one. For example training as a surgeon if you have a desire to cut and make others bleed! Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 207."},{"question":"Which one of the following terms was coined by Mary Ainsworth?","options":{"A":"Goodness of fi t","B":"Anaclitic depression","C":"Transitional object","D":"Separation individuation","E":"Secure base"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"According to Mary Ainsworth, attachment in infants helps to reduce separation anxiety. Infants use the attachment fi gure as a ‘secure base’ around which they can explore the environment. Chess and Thomas proposed the theory of goodness of fi t. They studied the innate psychological characteristics of every infant known as temperament. According to them, goodness of fi t results when the expectations and demands from mothers match the temperamental characters of the infant. Margaret Mahler described the theory of separation individuation. Anaclitic depression (hospitalism) was fi rst described by Rene Spitz in infants who had made normal attachments but were then suddenly separated from their mothers and placed in institutions or hospitals. These infants developed depression that was anaclitic (loss of dependent object) and recovered when their mothers returned. Sometimes, inanimate objects, called transitional objects (Winnicott) also serve as a secure base; these transitional objects are often soft toys or other commonly encountered things that often accompanies children as they investigate the world. For example, Hobbes in Calvin and Hobbes comic strips. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 280."},{"question":"Which of the following statements about attachment theory is INCORRECT?","options":{"A":"Abused children do not develop attachments to their abusive parents.","B":"The attachment of the fi rstborn child is decreased by the birth of a second.","C":"Stranger anxiety develops by 8 months.","D":"Separation anxiety occurs by 10–18 months of age.","E":"Children brought up in extended families or with multiple caregivers are able to establish many attachments."},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Abused children often maintain their attachments to abusive parents. Attachment behaviour can increase in the presence of hunger, sickness, or pain. Similarly when children are rejected by their parents or are afraid of them, their attachment may increase to some extent. Attachment develops in almost all children, but whether this is of a secure or insecure nature depends on multiple factors. Separation anxiety is a universal human developmental phenomenon emerging in infants less than 1 year of age and marking a child’s awareness of a separation from his or her mother or primary carer. Separation anxiety peaks between 9 and 18 months and diminishes by about 2.5 years of age, enabling young children to develop a sense of comfort away from their parents in preschool. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 137.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 131"},{"question":"A boy recognizes that the amount of water remains the same when transferred from a tall narrow glass to a wide-mouthed glass. Which stage of Piaget’s developmental model is he likely to have attained?","options":{"A":"Sensorimotor stage","B":"Preoperational stage","C":"Concrete operational stage","D":"Formal operational stage","E":"Conventional stage"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The concept of conservation develops in the stage of concrete operations. The primary sign that a child is still in the preoperational stage is that he or she has not achieved the concept of conservation or reversibility. Conservation is the ability to recognize that objects possess different compatible properties and the alteration of one property (e.g. height) does not necessarily alter other properties (e.g. volume). Conservation occurs in various dimensions – conservation of volume, quantity, number, area, and weight. Piaget’s stages of cognitive development include sensorimotor stage, which begins at birth and lasts up to 2 years. Object permanence and insight is gained in this stage. During the stage of preoperational thought (2–7 years), the child develops symbolic play and semiotic function. Children in this stage are egocentric. In addition to conservation and reversibility, the child also develops syllogistic reasoning in the concrete operational stage (7–11 years). Formal operational stage (11 to thr end of adolescence), is characterized by the development of the capability of hypothetico-deductive reasoning. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 136."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a projective test?","options":{"A":"Rorschach ink-blot test","B":"MMPI","C":"Sentence completion test","D":"Thematic apperception test","E":"Draw a person test"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The projective tests of personality assessment make use of unstructured stimuli, for example inkblots or pictures from which stories have to be derived. It is thought that when confronted with a vague stimulus, subjects will introduce (project) some personality characteristics into the stimulus. This will be revealed not only in the way the ambiguity is perceived but also in the content of their responses. The Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory (MMPI) is a self-report inventory with more than 500 true or false statements about oneself. It is an objective personality assessment instrument. The Rorschach Test is a standard set of ten inkblots which serves as the ambiguous stimulus for associations. In the Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) 20 stimulus cards depicting a number of scenes of varying ambiguity are used. Other projective tests include Draw a person test and sentence completion test. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 195–196."},{"question":"A 30-year-old man presents to rehabilitation services following a head injury. Which of the following is the LEAST useful test to measure premorbid IQ in this patient?","options":{"A":"Weschler’s Adult Intelligence Scale","B":"National Adult Reading Test","C":"Cambridge Contextual Reading Test","D":"Spot the Word Test","E":"Wechsler Test of Adult Reading116 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS) has a number of subtests, each tapping different aspects of intelligence. Verbal IQ is calculated based on the sum of the following subtests: vocabulary, similarities, arithmetic, digit span, information, and comprehension. Performance IQ is calculated from the sum of the following subtests: picture completion, digit symbol coding, block design, matrix reasoning, and picture arrangement. Three further subtests (symbol search, letter–number sequencing, and object assembly) have been added in later versions. National Adult Reading Test (NART), Cambridge Contextual Reading Test, Spot the Word Test, and Wechsler Test of Adult Reading are best used to test premorbid IQ. These measures are based on the observation that reading ability is relatively preserved in the face of organic cognitive impairment and is highly correlated with intellectual ability in the general population. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, pp. 142–143."},{"question":"Choose a suitable test to assess frontal lobe functions in a man suffering from head injury:","options":{"A":"Rey Osterreith test","B":"MMSE","C":"Wisconsin Card Sorting Test","D":"Stanford Binet Scale","E":"WAIS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST) is used to test set-shifting ability, which is thought to be a function of the frontal lobe. In Rey Osterreith Complex Figure Test (ROCFT) a complicated fi gure is presented and the subject is required to copy it. The original and copy are then removed and the subject is asked to draw the fi gure again from memory, after varying delay intervals. This is not specifi c for frontal lobe functions. Stanford Binet Scale measures general intelligence. Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) is a test of general cognition. In fact, it does not include any specifi c tests for frontal lobe function. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 146.132 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Among the WAIS subtests, performance on which of the following is relatively resistant to decline with ageing?","options":{"A":"Digit symbol","B":"Digit span","C":"Block design","D":"Similarities","E":"Picture completion"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Tests on WAIS are either ‘hold’ or ‘no hold’. The so called ‘hold tests’ in WAIS are thought to refl ect the use of old knowledge and are relatively resistant to the effects of brain damage and ageing. These include vocabulary, information, object assembly, and picture completion. ‘No hold’ tests require speed of response, working memory, or the creation of new relations between unrelated items. These are more likely to show early decline with ageing and cognitive impairment. These include digit symbol, digit span, similarities, and block design. This is the reason why WAIS is not the best test to measure premorbid intelligence. Groth-Marnat G. Handbook of Psychological Assessment, 4th edn. John Wiley & Sons, 2003, p. 178."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a bedside cognitive test?","options":{"A":"Halstead Reitan Battery","B":"Frontal Assessment Battery","C":"Verbal fl uency","D":"Category test","E":"Go–no go test"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The Halstead Reitan Battery is composed of seven to ten tests. The battery can differentiate those who are brain damaged from neurologically intact persons. It usually needs to be administered by a trained neuropsychologist and is time consuming. Frontal Assessment Battery is a battery of six tests used to test frontal lobe function at the bedside. It includes verbal fl uency, similarities, Luria three-step test, go–no go tests, and a test of environmental autonomy. In category test the subject must discover the common theme in a set of pictures presented. Category test measures concept formation and abstract reasoning. It is one of the tests included in the Halstead Reitan Battery. Verbal fl uency is measured using the FAS test. Groth-Marnat G. Handbook of Psychological Assessment, 4th edn. John Wiley & Sons, 2003, p. 520."},{"question":"Which of the following scales used in antidepressant trials is most sensitive to detect any change in the severity of depression?","options":{"A":"HAMD","B":"MADRS","C":"BPRS","D":"BDI","E":"PANSS"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression (HAM-D) and the Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) are two widely used depression scales. HAM-D is relatively limited in measures of sensitivity and multidimensionality but it is very popular. The MADRS (10 items), designed to be sensitive to treatment changes, is briefer and more uniform. A limitation of the MADRS is the lack of a structured interview, which may affect reliability. The HAM-D and the MADRS are often used conjointly as endpoints in depression trials. There are various versions of the HAM-D, ranging from 17 to 31 items. The Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS) comprises 16 items rated from 0 (not present) to 6 (extremely severe) and includes symptoms such as somatic concern, anxiety, depressive mood, hostility, and hallucinations. The scale was developed essentially for psychosis but also includes symptoms of depression. Positive and Negative Symptoms Scale (PANSS) is not a scale to measure depressive symptoms. It is used to measure the severity of psychotic symptoms. The Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) is a 21 question, self-report inventory. It is not a very useful measure of change in severity of depression with treatment. Iannuzzo R, Jaeger J, et al. Development and reliability of the HAM-D/MADRS Interview: An integrated depression symptom rating scale. Psychiatry Research 2006; 145: 21–37."},{"question":"While using a diagnostic rating scale, a psychologist tries to fi nd the degree of correlation between one test item and the other items in the scale. What is he trying to measure?","options":{"A":"Internal consistency","B":"Content validity","C":"Construct validity","D":"Split half reliability","E":"Test–retest reliabilityPSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 117"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Internal consistency is the degree to which one test item correlates with all other test items. Reliability is the consistency of a measuring instrument or the repeatability of a test. Inter-rater reliability is the likelihood that two raters will rate the same answer in the same way. Test–retest reliability is the degree to which a test will give the same result on two different occasions, separated in time. Parallel-form reliability is the extent to which two comparable versions of a test give the same result. Split-half reliability is when a test is notionally split in two and the two halves correlated with each other. Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 94.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 133"},{"question":"The results of a child’s IQ test relate signifi cantly to the occupational success he achieves when he grows into an adult. The test is said to have a high","options":{"A":"Construct validity","B":"Predictive validity","C":"Incremental validity","D":"Face validity","E":"Content validity"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Validity is a property that refers to whether a test measures what it is supposed to measure. Predictive validity is the degree to which a test predicts some criterion that might be achieved in the future (e.g. whether a child’s IQ test predicts occupational success when he/she grows into an adult). A test is said to possess good concurrent validity if scores on the test correlate with a gold standard or other diagnostic test used for the same purpose (e.g. if scores on HAMD are higher in those people with a severe rather than mild or moderate depressive disorder according to ICD 10, then HAMD is said to possess high concurrent validity). The above two types of validity together constitute criterion validity. Face validity refers to whether a test seems purposeful and sensible with regard to the tested domain to the person completing it. Content validity refers to the representativeness and relevance of the assessment instrument to the construct being measured. Construct validity checks whether a test measures a specifi ed and well-defi ned construct. For example, if a test is measuring depression, there should not be clusters of items that seem to measure symptoms of mania; the test should correlate with other measures of depression (convergent validity); it should not correlate with measures that are irrelevant to depression (divergent validity). Gelder MG et al., eds. New Oxford Textbook of Psychiatry. Oxford University Press, 2000, p. 94."},{"question":"Which of the following is a structured diagnostic instrument used in population surveys to measure disease prevalence?","options":{"A":"Young Mania Rating Scale","B":"Positive and Negative Symptoms Scale","C":"Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale","D":"Composite International Diagnostic Interview","E":"Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) comprises 11 items corresponding to the published core symptoms of mania. Four items are graded on a scale of 0–8 and have double weight; the remaining seven items are graded on a scale of 0–4. The Positive and Negative Symptom Scale (PANSS) is a 30-item rating instrument specifi cally designed to assess the psychopathology of schizophrenic patients. Subscores of the PANSS are positive, negative, general psychopathology, and affective symptoms composite scores. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) is a 14-item self-report scale that was developed originally to indicate the possible presence of anxiety and depressive states in medical outpatients. The Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS) is a 16-item scale with nine general symptom items, fi ve positive-symptom items, and two negative-symptom items. It is a clinician-completed scale often used in schizophrenia medication trials. Spiegel R and Aebi HJ. Psychopharmacology: An introduction, 4th edn. Wiley, 2003, pp. 198–202."},{"question":"Chris was confronted by a snake while hiking in a tropical forest. He later argued that the ‘fear’ he experienced was due to the tremors, muscle tension and sweating that occurred immediately upon seeing the snake. Which of the following theories is he using to explain the origin of his emotions?","options":{"A":"Cannon–Bard theory","B":"James–Lange theory","C":"Two-factor theory","D":"Opponent-process theory","E":"Schachter–Singer theory"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"He is using the James–Lange theory of emotions. According to the James–Lange theory of emotion, the perception of the stimulus leads to physiological arousal. The interpretation of the physiological arousal leads to the affective experience of the emotion. For example, ‘I feel afraid because my heart is pounding’. According to Cannon–Bard theory, perception of an emotionally relevant stimulus leads to the physiological and emotional arousal at the same time. Cannon and Bard attributed this to stimulation of the hypothalamus and the autonomic areas at the same time. In the Schacter–Singer theory (two factor theory), a person labels the pounding of the heart as fear because he appraises the situation of being in the midst of a snake as dangerous. So according to Schacter, the same physiological feeling can elicit different emotions depending upon the appraisal made by the subject from his situation. For example, pounding of the heart can be due to fear of the snake, anxiety secondary to exams and joy (or fear!) of meeting one’s spouse. Opponent-process theory is a theory of colour vision. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/ Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 190.134 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A psychiatrist wants to use a self-administered scale to assess the presence of depressive symptoms in a community-resident elderly patient. Which one of the following will he use?","options":{"A":"The Centre for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)","B":"The Carroll Rating Scale for Depression","C":"The Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS)","D":"Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale","E":"Hamilton Depression Rating Scale"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The CES-D is the most widely used screening instrument for depression in community- resident elderly because of the availability of normative population data. The GDS (Geriatric depression scale), developed specifi cally to screen older persons for the presence of depressive symptoms, has not been standardized for use in community populations. The Carroll Rating Scale for Depression, based on the Hamilton Depression Scale, has not been used extensively in elderly people. HAM-D includes many somatic elements of depression, which are often positive even in the absence of depression among elderly people due to high prevalence of physical health problems. It is observer rated and not self administered. BPRS does not look for the presence or absence of depression. Radloff LS. The CES-D scale: A self report depression scale for research in the general population. Applied Psychological Measurement 1977; 1: 385–401."},{"question":"Matthew is a 3-year-old boy referred to the local Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services (CAMHS) team with a history of poor scholastic performance. Which of the following scales is considered appropriate to evaluate his intelligence quotient?","options":{"A":"Stanford–Binet Scale","B":"Denver Developmental Scale","C":"Wechsler’s WAIS-R","D":"Wechsler’s WISC III","E":"Wechsler’s WPPSI118 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The Stanford–Binet scale is suitable for children between 2 and 4 years since it does not rely exclusively on language. It is also applicable for other age groups. The Denver Developmental Scale is used to assess the attainment of developmental milestones in children up to age 5. The WAIS-R (Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale) is used for individuals aged 17 and over. The WISC III (Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children) is useful for evaluating children aged 6–16. The WPPSI (Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence) is used for children aged 4–6. Groth-Marnat G. Handbook of Psychological Assessment, 4th edn. John Wiley & Sons, 2003, pp. 132–133."},{"question":"Classical conditioning has occurred when","options":{"A":"Unconditioned stimulus produces unconditioned response","B":"Conditioned stimulus produces the conditioned response","C":"Unconditioned stimulus produces the conditioned response","D":"Conditioned stimulus produces another conditioned stimulus","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The unconditioned stimulus (UCS) is a stimulus that evokes an unconditioned response (UCR) without previous conditioning, for example in the classic Pavlov’s paradigm, salivation (UCR) with food (UCS). UCR is not a learned response. Conditioned stimulus (CS) is a previously neutral stimulus that has acquired the capacity to evoke a conditioned response (CR) , for example the bell is the CS that is paired with food (UCS) which later elicits the salivation (now a CR). A fi rst CS (CS1) that has previously been paired with a UCS can support conditioning to a second CS (CS2) when the CS2 and CSl are paired together. Thus CS2, never directly paired with the UCS, still elicits a CR. This is higher-order conditioning. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 8."},{"question":"Repeated presentations of the conditioned stimulus in the absence of the unconditioned stimulus leads to a decrease in the strength of the conditioned response. This is known as","options":{"A":"Extinction","B":"Generalization","C":"Higher order conditioning","D":"Inhibition","E":"Recovery"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Extinction is the process by which CR is eliminated. After conditioning a CS to elicit a CR, repeated, subsequent delivery of the CS without the UCS extinguishes the CR. Three factors infl uence the extinction of the CR. In general, the stronger the CS–CR bond, the slower the extinction of the CR. When the CS is only occasionally presented during initial conditioning, resistance to extinction is increased. As the duration of the CS exposure in extinction increases, the CR weakens proportionately. Spontaneous recovery is the reappearance of an extinguished response after a period of non-exposure to the conditioned stimulus. Weiten W. Themes and Variations, 3rd edn. Brooks/Cole, 1995, p. 218.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 135"},{"question":"When Little Albert was conditioned to be afraid of white rats he also came to fear white lab coats and other white objects. This phenomenon is known as","options":{"A":"Extinction","B":"Satiation","C":"Generalization","D":"Discrimination","E":"Punishment"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Stimulus generalization occurs when an organism that has learned a response to a specifi c stimulus responds in the same way to new stimuli that are similar to the original stimulus. In this case, the colour white serves as the similarity between rats and lab coats. The closer the new stimuli are to the original conditioning stimulus, the greater the likelihood of generalization. Stimulus discrimination occurs when an organism that has learned a response to a specifi c stimulus does not respond in the same way to new stimuli that are similar the original stimulus. For example, a dog which wags its tails when it hears your car approaching the porch may initially wag when any car passes by (generalization). But as time goes, your faithful dog learns to discriminate the distinct sound of your car from your father-in-law’s car, who you may not like very much! The ‘Little Albert’ experiment mentioned in this question was conducted by Watson and Rayner in 1920. Albert was 11 months and 3 days old at the time of the fi rst test. Because of his young age, the experiment today would be considered unethical. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 107. Harris B. Whatever happened to Little Albert? American Psychologist 1979; 34: 151–160."},{"question":"The process by which the response to a stimulus declines with repeated exposure to that stimulus is known as","options":{"A":"Conditioning","B":"Sensitization","C":"Boredom","D":"Generalization","E":"Habituation"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Habituation and sensitization are two fundamental learning processes. In each case, animals change their reactions to a stimulus with repeated stimulation. Habituation is defi ned as a decrease in responsiveness to a stimulus, for example you may get habituated to the pressure on your toes from a new shoe when you wear it regularly. Sensitization refers to an increase in reactivity to the stimulus on repeated exposure, for example repeated listening to the new ring tone of your mobile may make you attend to the call quicker than on the fi rst few days of buying the phone. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 107."},{"question":"In a behavioural treatment, every time a person drinks alcohol, he is administered an electric shock. Which of the following principles underlie this treatment?","options":{"A":"Cognitive therapy","B":"Punishment therapy","C":"Systematic desensitization","D":"Aversive conditioning","E":"Psychodynamic therapyPSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 119"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Aversive conditioning makes use of the classical conditioning paradigm. Here an unwanted behaviour is paired with an aversive stimulus, thus eliciting an aversive response. Here the shock is not given as a punishment but it is given as an unconditioned stimulus (UCS) to which an unconditioned response (UCR), pain, will be elicited. By repeated pairing of alcohol (conditioned stimulus, CS) with electric shock, the pain (aversion) becomes a conditioned response (CR). Later drinking alcohol (CS) alone is expected to produce the CR of aversion and pain. Typically, a short, delayed conditioning paradigm is used (see Question 33), that is the patient is asked to pour alcohol into his mouth and half a second later a shock is delivered to his hand via an electrode. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 10–11."},{"question":"A 19-year-old girl visits the London Dungeon. Her startle response increases with each fearful stimulus. This phenomenon is related to","options":{"A":"Sensitization","B":"Habituation","C":"Systematic desensitization","D":"Relaxation","E":"Counter conditioning"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"This is an example of sensitization. Systematic desensitization is a therapy based on conditioning procedures that can be effective in the elimination of conditioned fear and the reduction of phobic behaviour. It has three steps: relaxation training, hierarchy formation, and exposure to the stimuli. By remaining relaxed while imagining the lowest item in the hierarchy, the fear of that situation or object is counter conditioned. In a similar fashion counter conditioning then proceeds to situations higher in the hierarchy. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 107.136 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"A 40-year-old lady is waiting to see her dentist after three painful extractions. She could hear the noise made by the dentist’s drill. This makes her feel anxious. This anxiety could be termed as which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Unconditioned stimulus","B":"Conditioned stimulus","C":"Conditioned response","D":"Unconditioned response","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The anxiety produced by the sound is the conditioned response (CR). Pain produced by the situation of drilling is the UCR. This is called fear conditioning and is one of the theories to account for the origin of phobias. When this classical conditioning paradigm is combined with operant conditioning, in the form of avoidance (negative reinforcement), a phobia is likely to have developed. So in fully developed dental phobics, not only there is anxiety produced by the noise of the drill, but also avoidance of the situation by not keeping the appointment (or waiting outside the waiting room). The stimulus itself may become generalized to a fear of all drills. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 15–16."},{"question":"Whenever Jack had to feed his pet dog, he would ring a bell in order to get its attention. He would stop ringing the bell before he served the meat. As days passed, the dog started salivating to the sound of the bell. Which of the classical conditioning paradigm is being used here?","options":{"A":"Trace conditioning","B":"Backward conditioning","C":"Delayed conditioning","D":"Temporal conditioning","E":"Simultaneous conditioning"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"This is an example of trace conditioning. There are fi ve paradigms that are used in classical conditioning. They differ with respect to how a CS is paired with a UCS. In delayed conditioning, the onset of the CS precedes the onset of the UCS and termination of the CS occurs either with the onset of the UCS or during UCS presentation. In trace conditioning, the CS is presented and terminated prior to the onset of the UCS. In simultaneous conditioning, the CS and the UCS have onsets at the same time. In backward conditioning, the UCS is presented and terminated before the onset of the CS. In temporal conditioning, the UCS is presented at regular time intervals allowing the timing of the UCS to serve as the CS eliciting the CR. Short delayed conditioning is the best arrangement that facilitates the acquisition of most conditioned responses. Ideally the delay between the onset of CS and UCS should be about half a second. Weiten W. Themes and Variations, 3rd edn. Brooks/Cole, 1995, p. 218. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 3, 4."},{"question":"Habitual consumption of paracetamol to relieve headache is related to which one of the following phenomena?","options":{"A":"Aversion","B":"Positive reinforcement","C":"Classical conditioning","D":"Negative reinforcement","E":"Punishment"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Negative reinforcement occurs when a response is strengthened because it is followed by the removal of an aversive stimulus. In this case, the headache. Other types of negative reinforcement include escape and avoidance learning. The term negative reinforcement should not be confused with punishment, which is an event following a behaviour which reduces the behaviour, for example stopping rash driving after getting a speeding ticket. Positive reinforcement occurs when a response is strengthened because it is followed by the presentation of a rewarding stimulus. For example a prize given for a desired behaviour increases the behaviour. It should be noted that both positive and negative reinforcements increase the behaviour in question. Punishment, on the other hand, decreases the behaviour. Weiten W. Themes and Variations, 3rd edn. Brooks/Cole, 1995, p. 230."},{"question":"Dave meets his girlfriend at a pub daily at 8 O’clock. As the time approaches, he keeps looking out for her more and more frequently through the window. This behaviour is suggestive of which of the following schedules of reinforcement?","options":{"A":"Fixed interval","B":"Fixed ratio","C":"Differential","D":"Variable ratio","E":"Regular120 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"In operant conditioning, the relationship between a response and the likelihood of reinforcement is known as a schedule of reinforcement. There are two major classes of schedules: (1) ratio schedules require a certain number of responses to produce reinforcement, and (2) interval schedules require a certain amount of time to elapse since the last reinforced response. Both types are subdivided into fi xed and variable. In a fi xed ratio schedule, a fi xed number of responses produce the reinforcement. For example, a rat is reinforced every 10 times it presses the lever. In variable ratio schedule, an average number of responses produce the reinforcement. It is similar to fi xed, but here the frequency of behaviour required to elicit the reinforcement changes after each reinforcement, for example slot machine in the casino pays off once every 10 times on an average, so it can take fi ve attempts for some while 15 attempts for others. The fi xed interval schedule involves a contingency in which reinforcement for a response is produced only after a specifi ed period of time has elapsed since the previous reinforced response, for example students earn grades after a test every 3 weeks. In this case, they don’t read during the initial weeks, but start reading just before the exam, that is the response increases just before the reinforcement. The variable interval schedule is the same as a fi xed interval schedule, except that the interval changes after each reinforced response, for example repeatedly dialling a phone number till one gets through to a lucky draw contest. When reinforcement depends on both time and number of responses, the contingency is called a differential reinforcement schedule. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 14.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 137"},{"question":"Which of the following schedules would most probably produce the greatest resistance to extinction?","options":{"A":"Fixed interval","B":"Fixed ratio","C":"Variable ratio","D":"Differential ratio","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Reinforcement for an operation in operant conditioning can be provided at various schedules. When every operation is reinforced this is called continuous schedule. Intermittent reinforcement can occur at a fi xed ratio (every third operation is rewarded), variable ratio (random rewards for operations), fi xed interval (operation that takes place at every fourth minute is rewarded), or variable interval (random time intervals for reward delivery). Though learning is relatively slower, resistance to extinction increases with partial reinforcement. The variable ratio schedule is the most diffi cult to extinguish. This is the principle behind slot machines and gambling addiction. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 14."},{"question":"According to Skinner, a reinforcement is defi ned as any event that","options":{"A":"Decreases a behaviour","B":"Increases a behaviour","C":"Increases or decreases a behaviour","D":"Is satisfying to the person","E":"Substitutes a punishment"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Reinforcement occurs when an event following a response increases an organism’s tendency to make that response. Primary reinforcers are events that are inherently reinforcing because they satisfy biological needs, for example food, water, sex, etc. Secondary or conditioned reinforcers are events that acquire reinforcing qualities by associating with primary reinforcers, for example money, good grades in exams, praise, etc. Weiten W. Themes and Variations, 3rd edn. Brooks/Cole, 1995, p. 222."},{"question":"Which one of the following is a true statement about learned helplessness?","options":{"A":"It was originally used as a cognitive model for depression.","B":"It occurs when met with uncontrollable aversive stimuli.","C":"It was fi rst described by Beck.","D":"It is one of the cognitive triads of depression.","E":"None of the above."},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The concept of learned helplessness was proposed by Martin Seligman. Seligman noted that when an animal is confronted with aversive stimuli from which escape is impossible, the animal stopped trying to escape. This was initially used as a behavioural model for depression. Cognitive triad of depression was fi rst proposed by Aaron T Beck. The triad consists of a negative view of self, the world, and the future, that is worthlessness, helplessness, and hopelessness. The triad forms the theoretical basis for cognitive therapy in depression. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 790. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 16."},{"question":"According to Seligman, people are more prone to develop phobia towards which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Electric heaters","B":"Knives","C":"Hot ovens","D":"Electric iron","E":"Darkness"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Seligman’s concept of stimulus preparedness involves a species-specifi c inclination to be conditioned in certain ways. He believed that this was a product of evolution and was necessary for the survival of species. Accordingly, genuine threats to the survival of our ancestors easily elicit phobic responses in humans, for example snakes, darkness, etc. Hence it is more common for people to develop snake phobias than to develop sheep phobias, even though they may never have had any direct adventure with a snake. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 107."},{"question":"A person who has never fl own develops a fear of fl ying. Which one of the following best explains the above process?","options":{"A":"Vicarious learning","B":"Flooding","C":"Operant conditioning","D":"Shaping","E":"Mowrer’s hypothesis"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Observational or vicarious learning (proposed by Albert Bandura) occurs when one’s behaviour is infl uenced by observing models. A model may be any signifi cant person or even an incident on television. So a person may develop a fear of fl ying after seeing an air disaster in a movie or a hijacking event on the television. Shaping is the progressive reinforcement of responses that are close to a desired response. This progressive reinforcement is continued until the desired response (usually a complex behaviour) is elicited. It is based on operant conditioning and works as the principle behind training animals to do circus tricks. Mowrer’s hypothesis puts forth a two-staged acquisition process for phobia wherein, initially, classical conditioning associates a fear response to a neutral stimulus. Later, through operant conditioning, this fear is maintained, as avoidance of the feared stimulus serves as a potential negative reinforcer. Note that in the scenario portrayed in this question there has been no previous exposure to the feared stimulus (fl ying). Hence operant conditioning and Mowrer’s hypothesis can be safely ruled out. Johnstone EC et al., eds. Companion to Psychiatric Studies, 7th edn. Churchill Livingstone, 2004, p. 108.138 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a part of gestalt theory of perception?","options":{"A":"Continuity","B":"Figure ground","C":"Proximity","D":"Shape constancy","E":"ClosurePSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 121"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Gestalt principle of perception is a theory of sensory information processing. Initially, any fi gure must be separated from its background. This is called the fi gure ground principle. The actual perception of the fi gure as a whole usually follows the principles of grouping. These are proximity, similarity, continuity, simplicity, common fate, and closure. The gestalt principle is based on the top-down processing of perception, that is a whole picture makes more sense and is easier to understand than parts of the same picture. In a similar sense, presenting letters one by one in random order of R, O, K, W, is more diffi cult to process than presenting the word WORK. The opposite, bottom-up processing, refers to a progression from individual elements to the whole. For example, bottom-up processing occurs when children initially learn to spell words. They initially identify each letter and then go on to learn to the whole word. A perceptual constancy is the tendency to experience an object as the same thing in spite of continually changing sensory input, for example we recognize an open door and a closed door as a door, irrespective of the differing geometry. Perceptual constancy includes concepts of size constancy, shape constancy, etc. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 244."},{"question":"Mark’s neighbours were robbed when they were on holiday. On hearing the news, he said to his wife, “They are such a careless lot. They must have left their doors unlocked. This will never happen to us”. He blamed the neighbours to minimize the apparent likelihood of a similar mishap to himself. This is best explained by","options":{"A":"Defensive attribution","B":"Fundamental attribution error","C":"Actor–observer bias","D":"Stereotyping","E":"Self serving bias"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Defensive attribution is a tendency to blame victims for their misfortune, so that one feels less likely to be victimized in a similar way. It also helps people to maintain their belief that they live in a just world. For example assuming that victims of a burglary were careless. Attributions are inferences that people draw about causes of events and behaviours – both their own and other person’s behaviours. Internal attribution attributes the cause to personal disposition. External attributions ascribe the cause to situational demands and environmental reasons. Fundamental attribution error refers to the process where an observer attributes others’ negative behaviour to their internal attributes. The systematic bias in attribution, when one’s own behaviour is assessed favourably compared to others’ behaviours, is called the actor–observer bias. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 218."},{"question":"Dave attributed his success in the Part 1 exam to his hard work and extensive knowledge of the subject. But when he fails his Part 2 he blames it on the examination system being poorly standardized. This is an example of","options":{"A":"The actor/observer effect","B":"Defensive attribution","C":"Stereotyping","D":"Self-serving bias","E":"Individualism"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Self-serving bias is said to occur when a person attributes his success to personal factors, while attributing his failures to external factors. It is a type of fundamental attribution error. Illusory correlation occurs when people estimate that they have encountered more confi rmations of an association than they have actually seen, for example after meeting one dishonest lawyer, a person makes a statement ‘I have never seen an honest lawyer’. Stereotypes are widely held beliefs that people have certain characteristics because of their membership in certain groups, for example lawyers are dishonest. Individualism is the process of defi ning one’s identity in terms of personal attributes rather than group membership. Collectivism is when one’s identity is defi ned in terms of group membership. Fundamental attribution error is seen less in collectivist cultures. Self-serving bias is seen more in individualistic Western culture. Naïve psychology, or common sense psychology, refers to certain propositional beliefs we hold about the actions and intentions of others in every-day life. These beliefs are socially conditioned and are necessary for human interaction. For example when someone waits in a queue to buy a train ticket, we infer that the person is travelling somewhere. These propositional ascriptions are not experimentally tested but heuristic and, in some cases, probabilistic assumptions. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 218. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 402.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 139"},{"question":"Holiday makers who pay hundreds of pounds for a trip to a water theme park will rate the park favourably even if it was boring and mundane. This can be explained using which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Self serving bias","B":"Learning theory","C":"Actor observer bias","D":"Dissonance theory","E":"Fundamental attribution theory"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"This is an example of postdecisional cognitive dissonance. Cognitive dissonance occurs when there is discord among a person’s different beliefs or behaviours. When a person experiences cognitive dissonance he/she changes his/her thinking or behaviour to lessen the disharmony. For example the owner of an expensive Porsche experiences a cognitive dissonance when the car breaks down on the motorway. He always believed that ‘Porsches do not break down’. Now he looks for alternative explanations. As a result of this dissonance he may change his belief as follows: ‘This is just a one-off event; this cannot happen again’. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 222–224."},{"question":"A depressed person who failed his recent maths exam says ‘I am stupid; I get everything wrong and will never pass any test’. The style of attribution in the above statement is","options":{"A":"Internal, unstable, and specifi c","B":"Internal, stable, and global","C":"Internal, stable, and specifi c","D":"External, stable, and unspecifi c","E":"External, stable, and specifi c"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"According to Seligman’s modifi ed theory of learned helplessness, depressed patients usually have attribution styles that are internal, stable, and global. It is ‘internal’ as they make causal attributions to internal personal traits rather than external events. These attributions are called stable as they are fi xed and held in spite of evidence to the contrary. They are global as they encompass all areas of functioning, for example in the scenario in Question 45, the person attributes to himself being stupid (negative and internal), will never pass a test (stable), and gets everything wrong (global). Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 219."},{"question":"In a famous experiment of animal behaviour, newly hatched goslings were observed to follow the actively moving experimenter. This process, where some young animals learn to follow the fi rst encountered moving object, is explained by which of the following?","options":{"A":"Vicarious learning","B":"Learning theory","C":"Imprinting","D":"Cognitive dissonance theory","E":"Premack’s principle122 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Imprinting, fi rst described by Konrad Lorenz is a form of learning that occurs in the very early life of certain animals. The exposure to a stimulus must occur during a critical period, though this could be of a short duration. Imprinted associations are very resistant to change. Lorenz described newly hatched goslings that are programmed to follow a moving object, typically the mother, but in this experiment followed Lorenz because he was the fi rst moving object they came in contact with. Imprinting does not depend on any reinforcement and it is not clear whether this occurs in human infants and all primates. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 159."},{"question":"‘If you eat your spinach, you can have your dessert’. This is an example of which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Cognitive dissonance theory","B":"Attitude behaviour similarity theory","C":"Inoculation theory","D":"Attitude incongruity","E":"Premack’s principle"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Premack’s principle is based on the concept that high-frequency behaviour can be used to reinforce a low-frequency behaviour. In this particular example, children eat a lot of sweets (high-frequency behaviour), but this can be made contingent on eating their greens (low- frequency behaviour), thus increasing this behaviour (also called the Grandma’s rule). Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 146."},{"question":"Brian is dressed shabbily when he walks into the New Year party for junior doctors. When he fi nds everyone in the room to be dressed at their best, he feels depressed and unattractive. Which of the following can explain the above?","options":{"A":"Social inadequacy theory","B":"Ideas of self reference","C":"Social comparison effect","D":"Conformity theory","E":"Social incompetence effect"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The Social Comparison Theory was developed by Festinger. It refers to an individual’s drive to look around him in the society to evaluate his own abilities. When the individual compares himself to someone who is deemed socially better, it is called an upward social comparison. The opposite is called a downward social comparison. Often individuals try to compare themselves with someone with whom they should be reasonably similar, for example their peers. The Self-Referential Encoding (SRE) effect holds that information relating to the self is preferentially encoded and organized above other types of information. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, pp. 469, 433.140 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"In a medical careers fair, most psychiatry trainees are noted to form a small social group on their own. The principle by which we categorize and identify ourselves as psychiatrists is explained by which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Social identity theory","B":"Self-reference effect","C":"Social comparison effect","D":"Social confi rmity","E":"Social incompetence"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Social Identity Theory is concerned with explaining when and why individuals act as part of social groups. At the psychological level it tries to answer why individuals identify with the group that they are a part of. At a social level, it tries to explain why individual interactions are different from interaction between individuals as members of different groups. The main concepts of social identity include:"},{"question":"Harry was recently diagnosed with an advanced carcinoma of the lung. He goes through a phase where he blames himself for the illness and asks ‘why me?’. Which one of the following stages of reaction to impending death is he in?","options":{"A":"Denial","B":"Anger","C":"Bargaining","D":"Depression","E":"Acceptance"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The stage of dying described in this scenario corresponds to that of ‘anger’. Kubler-Ross described the fi ve stages of dying in her book ‘Death and dying’. According to her theory, people’s reaction to impending death follows fi ve stages. The fi rst one being a state of denial, where the person is in a state of shock and denies the diagnosis of terminal illness. He may blame the doctor for giving him a wrong diagnosis. The second stage is that of anger, where the person becomes irritable and frustrated, often asking the question ‘Why me? ’ blaming himself or even God for being in the state he is in. In the third stage of bargaining, the person may try to negotiate with the doctor or family members or God to alleviate his illness in exchange of good deeds. Stage four is that of depression, where the cognitive triad of hopelessness, helplessness, and worthlessness are demonstrable. This may require treatment with antidepressant if severe. The fi fth and fi nal stage is of acceptance where the patient acknowledges and comes to terms with the inevitability of his/ her death. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 62. Kubler-Ross E. On Death and Dying. New York: Macmillian, 1969."},{"question":"After breaking up with her boyfriend, Tanya says, “I don’t think I have control over what is happening in my life”. Which of the following statements would describe Tanya?","options":{"A":"She is a person with a high self esteem","B":"She is a person with a great sense of direction","C":"She is a person with an external locus of control","D":"She is a person with an internal locus of control","E":"She is a person who has achieved self actualisationPSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 123"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Locus of control is a concept proposed by Julian Rotter as a part of his social learning theory of personality. Those with external locus of control attribute their successes and failures to external factors, for example luck, fate, etc. They believe that outcomes are largely out of their control. Those with an internal locus of control believe that success and failures are determined by their own action and abilities. There is some evidence suggesting that people with a high external locus are prone to more psychological problems. People with a high internal locus of control tend to be more successful. People with an external locus of control may be more prone to develop an equivalent of learned helplessness. For a given subject, locus of control may differ based on the issue considered. Consider the example – a person may feel that the political situation in his country is uncontrollable (external), but his own personal situation may be considered to be well under his control (internal). Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 203.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 141"},{"question":"A girl of age 2 years searches for her father when he leaves the room and is delighted when he enters the room. Which of the following phenomena explains this behaviour?","options":{"A":"The girl has achieved object permanence","B":"The girl has achieved semiotic function","C":"The girl has achieved syllogistic reasoning","D":"The girl has achieved hypotheticodeductive reasoning","E":"The girl has achieved the principle of centration"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Object permanence is the understanding that an object tends to exist even when it cannot be seen or touched. Piaget argued that very young infants did not have a concept of durability of objects, that is ‘out of sight is out of mind’. He claimed that the concept of object permanence was achieved by infants only during the late sensorimotor stage (at around 9 months). More recently this has been challenged by some studies (Hood and Willatts), which state that infants may start developing object permanence even as early as 5 months. Semiotic function is the process where children start to use a symbol or sign to represent an object. For example drawing is a semiotic function which may signify something in the real world. Semiotic function emerges during the preoperational stage. Syllogistic reasoning is the process by which a logical conclusion is formed from two ideas. For example crows are birds (premise 1); birds lay eggs (premise 2); therefore crows lay eggs (conclusion). This is developed during the stage of concrete operations. Centration is the tendency to focus on just one aspect of a problem, neglecting other important features. Centration is considered to be one of the basic fl aws in cognition, which leads to the inability of the child to understand the concept of conservation in preoperational stage. Hypotheticodeductive reasoning is considered to be the highest order of reasoning, where a person can develop a hypothesis and test it to reach conclusions. This function usually develops in the formal operational stage according to Piaget. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, pp. 135–137. Hood B and Willatts P. Reaching in the dark to an object’s remembered position: Evidence for object permanence in 5-month-old infants. British Journal of Developmental Psychology 1986; 4: 57–65."},{"question":"In Harlow’s classical study of rhesus monkeys, the baby rhesus monkeys preferred soft-clothed, non-feeding surrogate mothers to hard, wire mesh, but food-providing surrogate mothers. This illustrated the concept of","options":{"A":"Imprinting","B":"Individuation","C":"Insecure attachment","D":"Contact comfort","E":"Object relation"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Harry Harlow in his famous experiments in the 1950s separated rhesus monkeys from their mothers during their fi rst weeks of life. Harlow substituted a surrogate mother made from wire or cloth for the real mother. The infants preferred the cloth-covered surrogate mother, which provided contact comfort, to the wire-covered surrogate, which provided food but no contact comfort. Harlow suggested that the infant monkeys depended on its mother not only for nourishment, but also for physical warmth and emotional security, which he termed ‘contact comfort’. This is an important concept in attachment. Harlow’s experiment refuted the hypothesis that attachment occurs as a result of positive reinforcement to feeding. Imprinting is associated with Konrad Lorenz and geese. Harlow was not an object relation theorist; Klein, Fairburn, and Guntrip are considered to be object relation analysts. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 28."},{"question":"Predictors of delinquency include which of the following?","options":{"A":"Family history of aggression","B":"Family poverty","C":"Low IQ","D":"Lack of parental supervision","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Farrington et al. (see reference below) in their Cambridge study in delinquent behaviour identifi ed the following predictors of delinquency:"},{"question":"Ryan is late for his WPBA meeting with his supervisor. After waiting for half an hour at the bus stop, he realizes that all buses in this route have been cancelled due to bad weather. He swears and kicks a can of Coke lying on the ground in anger. Which of the following would best explain this behaviour?","options":{"A":"Ryan is angry with the litter on the ground","B":"Ryan is less polite when he is waiting for buses","C":"Frustration is associated with arousal","D":"Waiting for buses lead to an increase in blood pressure","E":"Bad weather leads to an increase in blood pressure"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"John Dollard’s frustration–aggression hypothesis states that aggression invariably stems from frustration and frustration in turn leads to aggression by arousing an individual. But frustrated individuals may react in various ways including resignation, depression, and despair. As a corollary not all aggression results from frustration, for example aggression exhibited during sporting activities such as boxing. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 151."},{"question":"Immigrant children in the UK tend to prefer the norms of their peers in the new culture compared to parental norms. Which one of the following could explain this?","options":{"A":"Immigrant children don’t like their original culture","B":"Immigrant children are compelled by their teachers to act like their peers","C":"Immigrant children want to pretend they are not immigrants","D":"Immigrant children need to act this way in order to survive at school","E":"Peers have more infl uence in transmitting cultural practices than parents124 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"An immigrant child often tends to conform to the norms of the peer group in his/her host country. Acculturation is the process of behavioural and attitudinal changes as a result of exposure to the practices of a different dominant group, usually seen in people who have immigrated. Children of immigrants born in the host country may achieve a high level of acculturation. The level of acculturation may differ in children born in the host country and those born elsewhere but later migrated to a host country. The degree and nature of the acculturation process is affected by age at immigration, number of years in the host country, language profi ciency, and participation in the host culture’s social activities, which is likely to be higher in school children, who are in constant contact with their peers, compared to adults. Martin A and Volkmar FR, eds. Lewis’s Child and Adolescent Psychiatry: A Comprehensive Textbook, 4th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 58."},{"question":"In spite of making a resolution to stop drinking, you place an order for a pint of lager when you see your friends place their order for drinks. Which of the following could explain the above phenomenon?","options":{"A":"Conformity","B":"Obedience","C":"Ignorance","D":"Acculturation","E":"Readiness"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Conformity occurs when people yield to real or imagined social pressure. If one listens to rock music in order to avoid being ridiculed by one’s friends and not because of one’s passion for the music then this exemplifi es conformity. The famous Asch’s studies in the 1950s provided most experimental background for studying conformity. Asch found that conformity was dependent on group size and group unanimity. People are more likely to conform when they are in ambiguous situations or when they have reasons to doubt their own judgement. Conformity is different from obedience. Obedience follows orders, comes from an authoritative fi gure, and the subject who obeys usually has no or reduced responsibility compared to the one who makes active decisions. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 204–206."},{"question":"In a famous experiment conducted by Milgram in the 1960s, a ‘teacher’ was instructed by an ‘experimenter’ to deliver shocks of high voltage to the ‘learner’ every time he made a mistake. Which of these factors infl uenced the decision by the ‘teacher’ to obey the ‘experimenter’?","options":{"A":"Diffusion of responsibility","B":"Perception of legitimate authority","C":"Persuasion techniques used by the authority","D":"Obedience to authority","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Obedience is a form of compliance that occurs when people follow direct commands, usually from someone in a position of authority. Diffusion of personal responsibility, legitimacy of the authority asking one to obey, strong persuasion techniques employed by the authority, and ingrained habit of obeying our parents and teachers as children infl uence our decision to obey authorities. Social groups depend on a reasonable amount of obedience to function smoothly. In Stanley Milgram’s experiment, the ‘learners’ were never really shocked. In fact the ‘teachers’ were the real experimental subjects, who believed that a shock was being administered. The “teachers” were asked to deliver the shock by an authoritative ‘experimenter’. Milgram’s experiments provided some explanations for certain aspects of human behaviour during atrocities such as the Second World War genocides. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 207."},{"question":"There are fi ve female PhD students living in a hostel for thirty at the university. Considering the girls to be the minority group, when will the group become infl uential in the hostel?","options":{"A":"If they are consistent with their views","B":"If they are joined by other girls and outnumber the majority","C":"When they complete their PhD","D":"When they spend a lot of money to infl uence the offi ce bearers","E":"If the minority consist of older people"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The minority in a social community may feel marginalized when their rights and needs are ignored. Members of the majority may be persuaded or infl uenced to change their attitude towards the minority by various means in order to reduce confl ict between the minority and the majority. In order to achieve this, the minority should present the required message consistently across all the members and through various time intervals. The minority should appear to be acting on principle and making personal sacrifi ce to become infl uential within a social group. Age composition or educational status of the minority does not have much effect on the overall infl uence posed by the minority in a group. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 205.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 143"},{"question":"Tony was considered to be a silent, shy and well behaved boy by his family and friends. At a rock concert he attended on his own, Tony was thrown out because of disorderly behaviour, which they considered to be out of character. His behaviour can be explained by the theory that when we are in a group which guarantees anonymity, we tend to","options":{"A":"Accept our individuality","B":"Become frustrated","C":"Assume an alternate identity","D":"Become disinhibited secondary to deindividuation","E":"Hide from the rest of the group"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Deindividuation is a psychological state in which an individual’s identity is lost among a collective mass of people and the markers of one’s individual personality are conspicuously absent. Anonymity leads to deindividuation and we tend to lose our inhibitions. Deindividuation prevents people from following the prosocial norms of society because they are unidentifi able and therefore feel less pressurized to follow the societal norms. Generally, deindividuation increases aggression unless a group adheres to prescribed codes of practice. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 506."},{"question":"A pianist is performing at a recital. According to the social facilitation theory which of the following is likely to happen?","options":{"A":"His performance can either improve or worsen in front of the audience","B":"His performance will improve when being observed","C":"His performance will worsen when being observed","D":"He will be supported by his community on contracting a disease","E":"He would be eligible for social benefi ts if he worked in a band rather than on his ownPSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS 125"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"According to the social facilitation theory, in the presence of others, a dominant response (i.e. a well-learned task) will improve, while a poorly learned response will worsen. For example a well-trained musician would, according to this theory, perform better in the presence of others, but a beginner will make more mistakes. It also depends on the involvement of the audience in the task and on the expectations of praise or criticism. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 204."},{"question":"A commercial sex worker receives an educational session regarding safe sexual practices from a health professional. She does not make any immediate change in her attitude or behaviour but agrees with the importance of such safe practice. Which of the following phases of Prochaska’s Transtheoretical Model of Change is she in?","options":{"A":"Preparation","B":"Precontemplation","C":"Contemplation","D":"Action","E":"Maintenance"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"The Stages of Change Model by Prochaska and DiClemente are stages that a person goes through when involved in a behavioural change. This may include a change in substance misuse behaviour, starting daily exercise, going on a diet or changing a health-related behaviour, for example attempting to obtain a cervical smear. The fi rst stage is precontemplation stage, where the person is not thinking of any imminent change and is happy the way things are. The second stage is contemplation where he is considering a change in the near future. Preparation is when he gets ready or prepares to make the change. Action phase is where he implements the change and in maintenance phase he decides to continue the change in behaviour and attempts to prevent relapse. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 125–126."},{"question":"A frail-looking young man suddenly collapses on a busy market street and starts throwing a fi t. In spite of the presence of many members of the public, no one comes forward to help him. Which of the following best explains the above observation?","options":{"A":"Social equity norm","B":"Diffusion of responsibility","C":"Social exchange theory","D":"Guilt","E":"Altruism"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"This observation is otherwise called the bystander apathy or bystander effect. People are less likely to provide help to someone in need if they are in a group rather than when alone. The probability of providing help decreases as the group size increases. One of the main reasons for the bystander effect is diffusion of responsibility, that is a thought that someone else might help. The other infl uencing factor is the perceived need for help. If it is an emergency situation, we are more likely to intervene and help. Altruism is a different concept and refers to selfl ess concern about the welfare of others that leads to helping behaviour. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, pp. 211–212."},{"question":"After receiving a small gift from a pharmaceutical representative, we feel indebted to prescribe the promoted drug. Which of the following could explain this behaviour?","options":{"A":"Social exchange theory","B":"Equity and equality norm","C":"The reciprocal norm","D":"Social responsibility","E":"Guilt"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The reciprocity norm is the situation where you help those who help you. This is a powerful social phenomenon utilized by pharmaceutical representatives. Social responsibility is the situation where you help those in need. Social exchange theory is a theory of interpersonal relationships. It regards relationships in terms similar to trading interactions. According to this theory, a relationship continues as long as both partners feel that the benefi ts of remaining in the relationship outweigh the costs of the same relationship. According to equity theory, a relationship is successful as long as both partners perceive that the individual outcomes from the relationship are proportional to their individual inputs. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 391. Schetky DH. Confl icts of interest between physicians and the pharmaceutical industry and special interest groups. Child and Adolescent Psychiatric Clinics of North America 2008; 17: 113–125.144 PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS"},{"question":"Margaret is 73-year-old. According to Erikson, she is most probably in the stage of","options":{"A":"Integrity verses despair","B":"Intimacy verses isolation","C":"Trust versus distrust","D":"Autonomy verses shame and doubt","E":"Industry versus inferiority126 PSYCHOLOGY | QUESTIONS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"This question tests one’s knowledge of Erikson’s stages of psychosocial development. Erikson’s stages were based on the concept of epigenetic principles. Epigenetic principle states that development occurs in sequential, clearly defi ned stages, and that each stage must be satisfactorily resolved for development to proceed smoothly. If a stage is not resolved satisfactorily, it results in physical, social, emotional, and cognitive maladjustment. In the question, the lady is 73 years old and is most likely to be in the stage of ‘Integrity versus despair’, where a person has to resolve the crisis between integrity (feeling at peace with oneself and the world, with no regrets or recriminations) and despair (feeling that life was full of wasted opportunities, regrets, wishing to be able to turn back the clock and have a second chance). Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 207."},{"question":"Chris is planning his stag party. He knows the average number of cans of lager a person is likely to drink. From that he calculates the number of cans he will need to buy, and in turn the costs involved. During this complex mathematical calculation, he manipulates numbers in his memory. Which of the following types of memory is he most likely to be using?","options":{"A":"Iconic memory","B":"Implicit memory","C":"Episodic memory","D":"Working memory","E":"Semantic memory"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Short-term memory (referred to by some psychologists as working memory) is a limited capacity store that can maintain unrehearsed information for about 20 to 30 seconds. This duration can be increased by rehearsing. The short-term memory, classically, is also thought to have a capacity of storing seven plus or minus two items. Because of this limited capacity, improving short-term memory storage requires a process called chunking, where identical data are grouped strategically to constitute a single chunk or item. Baddeley proposed an architecture for working memory. According to him, working memory involves three main components: a central executive, two ‘slave’ systems (the phonological loop and the visuospatial sketch pad), and an episodic buffer. The central executive coordinates the slave systems; the phonological loop contains a phonological store and an articulatory control process and is responsible for inner speech and rehearsing; the visuospatial sketch pad is responsible for setting up and manipulating mental images; the episodic buffer integrates and manipulates material in working memory. A sensory memory store holds a large amount of incoming perceptual information for a very short time, usually a fraction of a second before it can be processed. This store for visual items is called iconic memory and for auditory information is called echoic memory. Sensory memories have a lot of content and are of very brief duration. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, pp. 283, 293."},{"question":"A college student who last swam when he was 12 years old is surprised by his ability to swim when pushed into the pool during a party. Which of the following cognitive capacity could explain the above phenomenon?","options":{"A":"Procedural memory","B":"Retrospective memory","C":"State-dependent memory","D":"Eidetic memory","E":"Working memory"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Procedural memory is a type of memory wherein the knowledge of how to do things (procedures or skills, e.g. swim, ride a bike, typing, etc.) is stored. It may not be conscious. It is not easily communicable and practical demonstration is required. Declarative memory is something we are consciously aware of when we acquire it and we are able to communicate it to another person using language. Episodic memory is a declarative memory for events which can be recalled, for example remembering what one did last summer. It is defi ned by a specifi c time scale. Semantic memory is abstract knowledge retained irrespective of how or when it was acquired, for example ‘oceans are large bodies of water’. There is no time element attached to semantic memory. Gross R. Psychology: The Science of Mind and Behaviour, 5th edn. Hodder Arnold, 2005, p. 292; Fig. 17.7."},{"question":"A student preparing for a physics test learned the defi nitions of the following terms an hour before the test in this order: Hubble’s law, gravity wave, fusion, special relativity, string theory, and M theory. Which of the following defi nitions is he likely to forget?","options":{"A":"Fusion, special relativity","B":"Hubble’s law and m theory","C":"String theory and m theory","D":"Hubble’s law and gravity wave","E":"Gravity wave and string theory"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The serial position effect occurs when people show better recall for items at the beginning and the end of a list compared to those at the middle. This effect includes two components – the primacy effect, which occurs when items near the beginning of the list are recalled better than other items, and the recency effect, which occurs when items at the end are recalled better than other items. Thambirajah MS. Psychological Basis of Psychiatry. Elsevier, 2005, p. 160.PSYCHOLOGY | ANSWERS 145"},{"question":"The phase of human sexual response that occurs after desire is called","options":{"A":"Resolution phase","B":"Plateau phase","C":"Orgasmic phase","D":"Excitement phase","E":"Ejaculatory phase"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The stages of a normal male sexual response are desire, excitement, orgasm, and resolution. This is called the DEOR cycle. Traditionally it has also been described as the EPOR cycle, that is excitement, plateau, orgasm, and resolution. Sexual dysfunction can occur due to problems in any of the stages. Depression can lead to a loss of desire. Problems in the excitement phase can lead to erectile dysfunction; problems in the third stage can lead to premature ejaculation. Sadock BJ and Sadock VA. Kaplan & Sadock’s Synopsis of Psychiatry: Behavioral Sciences/Clinical Psychiatry, 10th edn. Lippincott Williams & Wilkins, 2007, p. 682."},{"question":"According to Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs Theory, at the times of natural disasters which of the following will be the most appropriate intervention?","options":{"A":"Provision of food and shelter","B":"CBT to enhance self-esteem","C":"Group therapy to enhance love and belongingness","D":"Behavioural therapy to enhance safety behaviour","E":"Meditation to achieve self actualizationchapter PSYCHOLOGY 4 ANSWERS"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"According to Maslow, human needs are arranged in a hierarchy. People must satisfy their basic needs before they can satisfy higher needs. Individuals usually progress upwards when their basic needs are relatively satisfi ed, but may regress back to lower levels. This is especially evident at times of huge natural disasters such as Tsunami or hurricanes. In order of needs, Maslow considered"}]');export{e as default};
